RG 170, Department of Developmental Services
Connecticut State Library
Dept. of Developmental Services records
1973-1994
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Dept. of Developmental Services
47 cubic feet
This record group consists primarily records of the Mansfield Training School that are described in a separate finding aid. Also included here are Commissioner's legal records from the lawsuit CARC v. Thorne, that resulted in the closing of Mansfield Training School, and a small quantity from the Community Services Division and Mystic Oral School Task Force.
RG170
Multiple
Historical Note
The Department of Developmental Services (DDS) has a long history in the State of Connecticut. As early as 1917, services for individuals with mental retardation were largely provided at the Mansfield Training School until 1940 when the Southbury Training School was opened. Eventually these facilities, along with “Regional Centers” established in the 1960’s, were overseen by the Office of Mental Retardation, a division of the State Department of Health.
In 1975 the Connecticut General Assembly established an independent Department of Mental Retardation (P.A. No. 75-638). The department has been a department in the executive branch, headed by a Commissioner appointed by the Governor, since that time. Although DDS continues to directly operate both congregate and community-based services and supports, the department's focus has largely become community-based relying upon a public/private partnership.
The result is a statewide system which provides support and services to persons with mental retardation who reside in family homes, independently, in state-operated facilities, in licensed "community training homes" and in over 830 licensed/certified "community living arrangements." Since 1987, most services and supports provided by DDS have been subject to federal reimbursement under Home and Community Based Waivers (Medicaid) which are approved by the Center for Medicaid and Medicare Services (CMS).
In 2007, the department changed its name from the Department of Mental Retardation to the Department of Developmental Services. This change reflects the mission and commitment of the department to serve individuals eligible for services with the utmost respect and dignity.
Source: State of Connecticut, Department of Developmental Services, History, (accessed on December 5, 2008).
See also the.
Scope and Content
These records include those from the same body under the previous name Department of Mental Retardation.
Subgroup 1, Mansfield Training School, 1863-1992, while part of this record group is described separately.
Series 2. Commissioner, 1978-1994, consists of legal files from the lawsuit CARV v. Thorne. The suit was filed in 1978 by the Connecticut Association of Retarded Citizens (CARC) against the Department and its Commissioner, Gareth D. Thorne. It was in the 1970s that community-based programs for the developmentally disabled began. In light of that change, CARC claimed that the administration and staff at Mansfield Training School violated their clients' 1st, 4th, 5th, 9th, and 11th amendment rights and sections of the federal Social Security, Developmental Disabilities and Rehabilitation Acts. After five years of litigation, the Department, the State, and the members of CARC negotiated an agreement codified in a Consent Decree. This Consent Decree contributed to the closing of Mansfield Training School. Included is client data, plaintiff files, depositions, studies, confidential correspondence and interactions with the Court Monitor's office.
Series 3. Community Services Division, 1973-1985, contains meeting material, block grant hearings, statistical summaries and listings of various grants and services, and policy mission statement and priorities.
Series 4. Mystic Oral School Task Force, 1983-1986, contains meeting material and correspondence related to the Task Force's activities for finding new uses for the Mystic Oral School property.
Arrangement
Arranged into Subgroup 1, Mansfield Training School; and three series: Series 2, Commissioner and Series 3, Community Services Division, Series 4. Mystic Oral School Task Force.
Related Material
RG 170:001, Mansfield Training School, 1863-1992.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Dept. of Developmental Services; Connecticut. Dept. of Mental Retardation
Subjects:
Connecticut. Dept. of Developmental Services -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut. Dept. of Mental Retardation -- Records and correspondence; Mental retardation patient facilities -- Services for -- Connecticut; Mental retardation patient facilities -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Connecticut; People with mental disabilities -- Care -- Connecticut; People with mental disabilities -- Institutional care -- Connecticut; People with mental disabilities -- Services for -- Connecticut; Developmentally disabled -- Institutional care -- Connecticut; Developmentally disabled -- Services for -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Correspondence; Depositions; Legal files; Reports
Restrictions on Access
Series 2 is RESTRICTED. Please contact State Archives staff for assistance.
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Subgroup 1. Mansfield Training School, 1863-1992
  Described separately at:
  Mansfield Training School Records
- Series 2. Commissioner, 1978-1994; 2006-020
  - Legal files
    - CARC v Thorne, 1978-1994
      The agency provided the following container list.
      This series is RESTRICTED. Please contact State Archives staff for assistance.
      - 87-401 - 87-1323 (Box 1)
      - 88-1 - 88-859 (Box 2)
      - 88-860 - 89-724 (Box 3)
      - 89-92 - 89-723 (Box 4)
      - 89-91 - Miscellaneous client data files (Box 5)
      - Other miscellaneous suits (CIB, WORC) (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
      - 94-1 - 94-15; 93-1 - 93-20; 92-20 - 92-91 (Box 8)
      - 1980s (Box 9)
      - 90-1 - 91-79 (Box 10)
      - 1980s - Early 1990s (Box 11)
      - 91-81 - 81-88; Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 12)
      - 84-1 - 84-23; 85-1 - 85-676 (Box 13)
      - 85-677 - 86-880 (Box 14)
      - 86-81 - 87-400; Miscellaneous files (Box 15)
      - Miscellaneous 1985 - 1986 (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous lawsuits; QAIG reports (Box 17)
      - Lensink files (Box 18)
      - Lensink files (Box 19)
      - Plaintiff info - C. Daly (Box D-1)
      - Plaintiff info - C. Daly; Nancy Ray report & rebuttal; Longitudinal study, miscellaneous (Box D-2)
      - Assorted study's report - C. Daly (Box D-3)
      - Lyn Gravink files, miscellaneous (Box D-4)
      - Lyn Gravink files; Miscellaneous C. Daly; Miscellaneous health care plan (Box D-5)
      - C. Daly files (Box D-6)
      - Miscellaneous suits - C. Daly (Box D-7)
      - C. Daly (Box D-8)
      - Miscellaneous files - C. Daly (Box D-9)
      - T. Richardson (Box D-10)
      - Depositions (Box D-11)
      - Depositions exhibits (Box D-12)
      - Depositions/Correspondence 1980s (Box D-13)
      - Bennett Hall - Mansfield Training School (Box D-14)
      - Interrogatories (Box D-15)
      - Client contractual agreements (Box D-16)
      - Client contractual agreements; Southbury Training School v. DOJ (Box D-17)
      - Plaintiff files - D. Avis 1985 (Box D-18)
      - Plaintiff files - D. Avis 1985 (Box D-19)
      - Plaintiff files - Rittinger, Meli, Rotonto, Teitelman (Box D-20)
      - Plaintiff files - Ogrean, Brilla, Riccardi, Rogers, Arnold (Box D-21)
      - Plaintiff files - French, Sandahl, miscellaneous plaintiff materials (Box D-22)
      - Miscellaneous testimony depositions (Box D-23)
      - Miscellaneous files - J. Grundel (Box D-24)
      - Contractual agreements (Box D-25)
      - Southbury Training School - Dober v. Thorne; Miscellaneous Thorne (Box D-26)
      - Webster Hill House hearing - T. Richardson (Box D-27)
- Series 3. Community Services Division, 1973-1985; 1999-008
  - Records, 1973-1985 (Box 1)
    - Community Service meetings, 1 binder (Box 1)
    - Day care, diagnostic clinic and vocational training grant-in-aid, 1961-1975, 1 binder (Box 1)
    - Listings of various populations at various activities, locations, 1 binder (Box 1)
    - DMR policy #9: Standards for the use of intervention techniques with clients of the Department of Mental Retardation, 1981 September; 1 folder (Box 1)
    - Hearing transcript, Bridgeport, regarding social service block grant, 1983 July 14; 1 folder (Box 1)
    - D D Distribution: Developmental disabilities grant program, 1 binder (Box 1)
    - Hearing transcript, Hartford, regarding social service block grant, 1983 July 14; 1 folder (Box 1)
    - Specialized training program: Model school and community services for people with severe handicaps, 1982 March; 1 report (Box 1)
    - A summary of mental retardation and developmental disabilities expenditures in the United State: FY 1977-1984, 1 report (Box 1)
- Series 4. Mystic Oral School Task Force, 1983-1986
  - Records, 1983-1986 (Box shared box)
    The Task Force explored uses for the Mystic Oral School property.